Joining us now
Speaker 1: is independent journalist and the world's foremost expert on the contrarian perspective
Speaker 2: of the entire Jeffrey Epstein saga. He is Michael Tracy. Michael, welcome back to the Death of Journalism podcast. Well,
you start off by calling
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): me both an expert and a contrarian, which are two terms that I disavow.
really
Speaker 4: which maybe maybe
Speaker 5: underscores what a contrarian i am i guess but
Speaker 4: you know just because everybody always calls me a contrarian you
Speaker 7: don't think you're an expert on the case
Speaker 8: um i wouldn't go around like self-declaring that i have like an expertise per se because like i
Speaker 9: just hate when people get described as like i don't know a terrorism expert or you know public health experts
Speaker 10: were a big problem during covid just this whole conceit of experts and expert the expert class and expertise, I kind of
had
Speaker 10: an aversion to and then as for contrarian that's
a charge
Speaker 10: that's get that gets leveled at me constantly you know well predating the epstein thing it's to almost
like in
Speaker 10: lieu of addressing anything i say on the substance try to almost say psychologically diagnose me of having some kind of like personality pathology that is like the true motivation for for what i do so i just find it to be sort of an
Speaker 11: annoying almost uh deflection that people
Speaker 1: use michael first of all it's
Speaker 1: In my bio and my ex-feet, I call myself a contrarian. So I consider contrarian in this age to be a compliment.
Speaker 12: You might,
Speaker 10: but for most people, I find it denotes some kind of arbitrary urge or compulsion to just needle people by automatically taking a
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): position that is contrary to theirs.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): As though, like, you haven't done your own independent reasoning or reporting or whatever to come to the view that you have. You've only done it
Speaker 13: because you want to do,
like, a mirror
Speaker 13: image of what the prevailing view is.
Well, no,
Speaker 14: there's a – I don't want to get sidetracked here, but you've come to a contrarian
Speaker 12: position on this case because you actually did the research and are an actual expert on it. A
Speaker 15: contrarian is like a personality type in the way that I've interacted with
Speaker 10: that claim for the most part.
Speaker 10: Yeah, the view that I've taken on Epstein is contrary to the Pirelli one, sure. But it's not more of like a just contrarian,
Speaker 16: intrinsic sort of instinct. Nor
was that
Speaker 16: ever intended to be the reason why I used that description.
Speaker 17: See, I'm giving you a hard time already. We're off to a fantastic
Speaker 18: start. Now, you've been very busy. You've done a ton of interviews since the bulk of the release. I've got to
Speaker 19: start turning them down, I think, at some point. But I don't have the discipline to – Okay, well, you didn't
Speaker 20: want to turn this one down because this one,
Speaker 20: is a fellow contrarian.
Speaker 19: Because you're always so soothing and calming to interact with.
Speaker 18: And we both understand the case, which is very unusual in this media environment.
Speaker 21: You've said in one of the many interviews that you believe that the entire Epstein saga is the worst reported case in decades. And since this is the Death of Journalism podcast, I want to start our conversation there. On what did you base that? And is this a new conclusion you've come to post-
Speaker 21: release of the Epstein files? I think
I
Speaker 8: said it was the worst reported story. So not necessarily just a criminal case, per se,
because
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): obviously the Epstein issue transcends just the mere criminal case that was brought against Epstein or that Epstein pleaded guilty to or Maxwell or what have you. You know, it's taken on such a magnitude now that it's almost like this mega narrative or something that, again, just goes way beyond a simple criminal matter.
So
Speaker 10: that's what I meant, and I said that because of all the political ramifications, right? And because it's also become a pop cultural fixation. Like people who are apolitical
or not
Speaker 10: overtly political, meaning maybe don't have a strong partisan affiliation or wouldn't day-to-day engage with
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): political news, they're very into this now. I just heard somebody relayed an anecdote
to me
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): about...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): zoomers i mean i hate those generational labels but like you know people in their teens maybe early 20s or something
among
Speaker 10: whom as far as this person could observe to be
skeptical in any
Speaker 10: way of the prevailing error is what now makes you an outsider meaning you're the insider or it's just commonplace or assumed that everybody in that age cohort
to the
Speaker 10: extent this issue would ever come
up
are
Speaker 10: going to be saying things like, yeah, of course we're ruled by satanic
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): pedophile cabals and they've covered everything up and maybe Trump isn't on it or maybe Clinton went to the island, et cetera. Stuff like that kind of
Speaker 10: common interpretation is what is
just the
Speaker 10: standard, whereas now you're an outsider if you evince
Speaker 23: the slightest bit of skepticism toward any of it, whereas in the past, you've got to think it would kind of be the reverse where somebody who is babbling
Speaker 10: that
–
say
Speaker 10: occult pedophiles are like pulling the strings in society and they're the source of all power in terms of how our
international order is governed
Speaker 10: or something they would be seen as like this bizarre crank who's like uh yammering to themselves in the corner or something with a tinfoil
Speaker 23: hat right but now that's the that that's the prevailing commonplace view so i think that you know the the tenor of the coverage the nature of the coverage
is
Speaker 10: across all different media so talking about social media you know broadly construed mainstream media alternative media
it's all
Speaker 10: congealed together to create this holy fictitious perception that is now so ubiquitous that has led people in that age cohort for example to just kind of like almost unthinkingly absorb what they assume the truth of matter to be that is so divorced from the
actual facts and evidence that
And I
Speaker 10: said it's the worst issue because just look at what's going on now, right? I've said for months that one of the reasons that I'm motivated to cover this issue so closely, it gets so engrossed in it, is because for one thing, among others, but for one thing, it is encouraging the proliferation of widespread misdiagnoses of legitimate political problems, meaning people are being told to view
Speaker 10: Unrelated political problems whether to do with foreign policy or other issues through the lens of Epstein right because if everything really is governed by this like Israel connected honeypot operation that ensnared all these prominent individual individuals in blackmail then that should be what people assume to be the genesis of like for example the United States
Speaker 8: going to war with Iran or Trump bombing Iran and then like that's like if you look at any social media platform nowadays.
That's
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the consensus opinion, meaning Trump went to war with Iran because of –
Speaker 24: I don't know that it's the consensus opinion in the public, Michael, maybe on portions of social media. I'm
talking
Speaker 23: about social media in particular, which kind of does correlate to some degree nowadays with broader public opinion, not
Speaker 10: perfectly, but definitely among the younger demographics.
Speaker 25: Maybe. So what you just said there is important,
Speaker 26: and I want to make sure that we break it down again from the media perspective.
One
Speaker 26: of the
Speaker 21: things that has been most striking to me about this story, and I have come to your belief that this may be the worst reported story in
Speaker 27: modern history, which is saying something because there's been a lot of really, really bad examples.
Speaker 28: John Ziegler is willing to is willing to dislodge Sandusky as the worst covered story.
Speaker 28: For Epstein, that's a big development.
Speaker 26: Well, I am willing to acknowledge that as of today, and it's only been in the last couple of weeks, I now actually believe that this has been more poorly reported than the Sandusky-Penn State-Paterno
Speaker 27: case. Ding, ding, ding, ding, ding, confetti drop. However, I'm not sure it's been worse than the COVID
Speaker 26: panic.
Speaker 26: And then the COVID panic created way, way, way more damage. But I don't want to get into a debate over which was worse. I want to explain what you just said, maybe a little bit more precisely. In a previous era, the
Speaker 30: mainstream legacy powerful media outlets would have been against the side of
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): conspiracy. They would have been against the side of this crazy worldview that you articulated. Instead, because of unique circumstances,
they have
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): have embraced fully and
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): blindly this view of the world. And I'm curious, do you believe it's because they really truly believe that that's what happened in the story or because their incentive structure is perverse
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): in this situation, partially because of the popularity of the story, as well as the unique politics of it, where the MAGA media became invested for one reason, the liberal media became invested because they thought they might get Trump. Which is it to you?
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): you think they truly believe i'm talking about the major media outlets do they
Speaker 14: really believe this or are they just going along asking questions because they know it's good for them well
let me give you an
Speaker 13: amazingly instructive example of this that popped immediately into my mind when
you
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): were spelling out your your thesis there
so
I had a
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): column that was published in the Wall Street Journal recently. We talked about it, right? I think, I don't know for 100% certain, but my sense
Speaker 10: is that it's the only column of its kind or, you know, article
of its
Speaker 10: kind or, you know, media offering of its kind that's been published
Speaker 33: in a major American media outlet from, like, my rough perspective, okay, on any aspect of this.
Your
Speaker 34: contrarian perspective is what you're saying. Your contrarian perspective. If
you
Speaker 23: must label it that. Sorry.
But
Speaker 23: then, you know, somebody texted me, actually somebody in a major media institution who pretty much agrees with me and actually got a primer from me because they requested
it a
Speaker 23: couple of months ago. And,
you
Speaker 33: know, on occasion,
we'll weigh in on
Speaker 33: something Epstein related, but like it doesn't go full bore with it, really. They have to be pretty calibrated.
Speaker 33: but they sent me this article that got published in the Wall Street Journal just a few days after my column. Now, my column was in the opinion section. It's run by a different editorial structure than the news section. This is in the news section, and here's the headline. March 7th. For some
Speaker 8: influencers, Epstein conspiracy theories are a big business.
Speaker 23: So this is the Wall Street Journal going through some of the more just like wildly outlandish stories.
Speaker 10: Spins on the Epstein story that get a lot of play
on the
Speaker 10: Internet, on social media, and who some of these conspiracy-oriented media profiteers
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): have chosen to...
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): amplify ad nauseam and it's a big business for them, right? So they go through Alex
Speaker 35: Jones, they go through streamers
Speaker 10: I never heard of, like quote unquote true crime podcast people who I would never have heard of, like just the flood of insane stuff that's on TikTok and whatever. But then the
reason why
Speaker 10: this article is pointed
Speaker 23: out to me, because over the course of this article that at least purports to be documenting and
Speaker 23: presuming to be untrue some of the most wildly outlandish takes on Epstein here here's what they say
quote still the
Speaker 23: Epstein files might
Speaker 8: represent a unique bonanza as conspiracy fodder goes for one thing what once seemed fantastical
That
Speaker 8: an evil man and his posh British girlfriend were abusing
Speaker 10: dozens of girls on a James Bond style private island and chumming around with a prince and a former U.S. president has now been proved true. So hold on, record scratch. It
has
Speaker 23: not, it has emphatically not ever been, quote, proved true that dozens of
girls were
Speaker 23: abused on the private island in the U.S. Virgin Islands, much less that Ghislaine Maxwell was involved in abusing any girls on the island.
Speaker 23: private island. I don't even know where that claim came from, and yet it's being presented as true in an article that is otherwise about highlighting the ridiculousness of some of the prevailing Epstein theories, right? So why is this instructive? Because even among the more mainline press, right,
where
Speaker 10: they're willing
to sort
Speaker 10: of point and chuckle and even maybe bemoan the crazier theories that have been percolating on the internet around Epstein,
right?
They still
Speaker 36: buy into all the main premises that have given rise to why this has become such a massive story and a mass hysteria and a moral panic, such as that this island, for example, was...
Speaker 23: Like the site of the biggest rape atrocity in history and like pedophiles were flocking to it and so forth. Like that's just like baked in here as a premise that they assume to be true without any examination at all. Again, amazingly enough, an article is otherwise like rebutting the more unsubstantiated
Speaker 26: theories. What you just said there is that the mainstream media has accepted a false premise.
They
Speaker 26: don't have any incentive to debunk that premise, especially now, because
Speaker 30: it's been so accepted. And that premise is the prism through which they have seen all of this allegedly new information coming from the Epstein files,
Speaker 21: much of which is total garbage and is also being seen through an incorrect prism, which we're going to get to momentarily. But it's interesting to me that you mentioned the Wall Street Journal. And since we started this with...
Speaker 21: This is the worst reported story in recent times with maybe
Speaker 28: with maybe with the worst repercussions, too. That's also
Speaker 9: a factor in why I would call it not compared to
Speaker 37: COVID. But again,
I
Speaker 9: don't know. I just don't I don't know that they're quite analogous, but let's not get derailed.
But
Speaker 27: anyway, here's my point about the Wall Street Journal. And I'm curious, since you know more about this than anybody I
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): know and probably anyone in the world.
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): I have been startled by just how bad the media has been in general, but specifically News Corp owned print outlets, specifically the Daily Mail and specifically the New York Post, which I normally like. Wall Street Journal is under that umbrella. They have done some really horrible work the journal has done, but they also published your column and they've done a couple other things that have been decent. Do you agree that News Corp outlets have
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): have been the worst and do you have any
Speaker 38: explanation for this
Speaker 39: interesting
Speaker 10: question you know a couple months ago right before the new york uh mayoral election i
had a
Speaker 10: featured story column in the print edition of the new york post i had written for them once before a couple years ago but this was like the first sort of major piece i had
for them and it was on
Speaker 10: uh andrew cuomo
uh
And
Speaker 10: how Zoran Mamdani had resurrected some of these phony old quote-unquote sexual harassment
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): allegations, and he paraded out onto the debate stage one night with one of the supposed survivors of Andrew
Speaker 40: Cuomo.
And
Speaker 40: like the severity of the conduct that was even alleged vis-a-vis Cuomo is just like laughable, at least with Epstein, right? They're alleging that there was like some kind of pedophilic
Speaker 10: rape going on. So how does this relate to
Speaker 42: their Epstein coverage?
Speaker 10: Well, because I'm just indicating to you that the New York Post in that instance is willing to take sort of like a counter-narrative position on something. Right. No, no,
Speaker 36: I like the Post. They even intersected with sexual harassment, sexual assault, whatever. But that's why I say that Epstein is the worst coverage story because it just –
Speaker 36: engulfs everything it engulfs media from across the spectrum that might otherwise be disposed to take a more critical eye toward this sort of thing you would think but like epstein has become
Speaker 43: this like singular totemic issue with all this kind of like folklore that right i
Speaker 44: know this is this is going to be a very difficult on the
Speaker 45: on the news corp on papers i mean the daily mail was hugely central in sort of
Speaker 45: The genesis of the Epstein
Speaker 33: story, in a sense, because they're the ones who sent a reporter to Australia in 2011 to interview Virginia Roberts Gouffre and pay her $160,000 plus serialization
Speaker 23: revenue and hand over the infamous photo of Prince Andrew, a purported photo.
And that
Speaker 23: got published. It created a minor firestorm. And then the journalists...
Speaker 33: Sharon Churcher starts conniving with Virginia Roberts Goufray to try to marshal into some kind of book deal or entertainment deal. So that's when they say to themselves, hey, let's just throw in whatever like
big
Speaker 46: name person we can think of into the book manuscript so that'll entice the literary agents or
Speaker 33: publishers to give you the biggest possible advance.
So the
Speaker 33: Daily Mail has always been a huge player in this.
Speaker 10: And I don't know, I would consider the Wall Street Journal any worse than like
Speaker 10: CNN or... No, but
Speaker 47: I would have expected the journal... I would have been expected more from the journal. They've been disappointing, except for a couple of
Speaker 27: examples. The New York Times actually did an article that the Epstein files should never have been released, which I agree with, and they got enormous amounts of backlash. The Atlantic
Speaker 21: magazine tried to push back...
Speaker 21: and they got destroyed as well. It's almost like they're being accused of blasphemy for
Speaker 27: going against the religious nature of the narrative in this case. But I don't want to relieve this portion of the conversation without any specificity. And this is going to be a very difficult question for you to answer succinctly, but I'd like you to try to be as focused as possible because there's so many bad examples
of
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): horrendous reporting in this case. I'm curious which is the one or maybe two
examples
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): Worst examples in Michael Tracy's mind of things that have been completely botched by the news media. I mean, for instance, just in the last week or so, this New Mexico rant situation is completely preposterous. Resources are being used to search for two girls that never even existed, that supposedly...
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): were killed by Epstein. The
Speaker 30: state police have been
Speaker 48: searching the ranch this week. They have like a search warrant and they're doing a raid on the ranch with radar equipment.
Speaker 49: Michael Chasey, give me a zero to 100. What are the percentage chances that they will find anything remotely closed to dead bodies related
Speaker 50: to Epstein? As
Speaker 45: far as I can tell, the entire basis for them watching literally a new criminal investigation, not just like maybe saying they're going to look into something,
Speaker 51: but it's a new criminal investigation initiated by the
Speaker 51: the state attorney general's office where the state police or the investigators, right? It
was
Speaker 23: based on an email that got swept up into this latest Epstein Files production. And this is going to sound almost too bizarre to possibly be true, but it is. Where
a Bitcoin
Speaker 23: scammer, an anonymous Bitcoin scammer, emailed a Albuquerque, New Mexico radio DJ in 2019 saying...
look I
Speaker 23: happen to know that where the there are bodies that are buried at the Zorro ranch and I'll tell you if you transfer
Speaker 10: me over x amount of bitcoin but only upon the completion of the transaction will I tell you the location of these bodies right and then the radio DJ I guess forwarded to the FBI and then it gets put out in this tranche of files and it's taken I guess as presumptively
Speaker 51: true on some level or at least true credible enough that it could serve as the basis for like a literal whole new criminal investigation. So like, what's the basis for anybody
thinking
Speaker 45: that they need to haul radar equipment to the Zorro ranch to check for dreary bodies that's it I think so like I don't know I guess like the moon could
be made
Speaker 45: out of cheese or
Speaker 23: you know it's like technically possible on some like infinitesimal
level
Speaker 23: But you know, maybe they'll find like an ancient body that was buried in like,
Speaker 33: you know, like the prehistoric era. And then they'll claim that it's like an Epstein casualty or something. Who knows what they could come up with. But see, but
Speaker 52: see, to me, the New Mexico story week, that's just one of the crazier ones this week, not even be the craziest. Well, but I think it's an important story because I
Speaker 27: think it goes to the broader problem with the release of the so-called Epstein files.
Speaker 27: Somehow, this trove of whatever you want to call it, information, has been deemed by the media and by huge portions of the public to have inherent value or credibility, I
Speaker 53: think, because...
We
Speaker 53: weren't allowed to see it, or at least in perception, it was being kept
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): from us. And therefore, because it was being kept from us, there must be some inherent value to this. You always want most what you can't have. When in reality, I keep referring to the Epstein files as largely, while there's some interesting stuff in there, especially his communications, which we know to be real.
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): For people who are into the case, I'm sure that there's some context to some of what really did and did not transpire here. But to me, the vast majority of the stuff that's getting media coverage is literal garbage. It's a garbage dump where crackpots,
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): insane people, people looking for attention, people maybe looking for money.
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): People with a political agenda against
Speaker 54: Donald Trump. And that's the stuff that goes well on social media. That's the stuff that gets
Speaker 23: clipped out or screenshotted and blasted out on social media as well, which is – I mean it's only a tiny percentage of the overall files. It's not that I've looked through every – several billion of them yet.
But do
Speaker 23: you agree – But there is actually interesting material in these files. You've got to know what to look for, right? You have to have some kind of research methodology rather than typing in pizza and then like
Speaker 40: –
Speaker 40: Trumpeting like some email that's decontextualized from 2013 or something that seems a little bit odd out of context and claiming that must be code word for pedophilic.
Speaker 56: Michael, do you agree with me that the fundamental problem when it comes to reporting on things that come
out
Speaker 30: in the Epstein files is that the credibility and the value of the information is absolutely.
Speaker 30: Being exponentially
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): overrated for whatever psychological and political reasons that the reality is there's a good reason why we never find out about this
Speaker 57: stuff. You and I talked
on
Woman 58: the phone. There's stuff that could be credibly represented to the public that gets just ignored. Right. So, for
Speaker 23: example, one of the first things that actually was notable and revelatory that I came across because I have a particular research sort of methodology, let's
say, is.
Speaker 23: Where I'm not just like fishing for whatever I can like impute some kind of sinister pedo meeting
to was that
Speaker 9: this number of over a thousand victims that's been repeated ad nauseum by Republicans and Democrats by across the media since last July.
Speaker 23: Right. Because it was in that dopey, self-defeating memo that the DOJ and FBI put out last July.
Speaker 23: Where they say in like weasel word language that they found, despite all the common mythology being untrue, they say in this memo, they nonetheless found that over a thousand victims were, quote, harmed by Epstein, right? And so that got repeated and regurgitated to emphasize the enormity of Epstein's
views.
Speaker 9: predatory conduct right that had gone unpunished and led people to assume if they see that giant figure that how could Epstein have done
Speaker 36: that alone like that's kind of like a reasonably intuitive reaction right and it turns out to be total propaganda how do we know because there are files actually in these Epstein files where the FBI in these internal communications are discussing the providence of that number it's totally it's
Speaker 23: like grossly inflated it includes
The
Speaker 10: family members are purported victims, the majority of whom are going to be adults rather than children, and yet we're called this is a pedophile scandal, like of epic proportions, right?
Speaker 36: So that's like an actual revelation, but have you seen that reported anywhere? I mean, I
did a
Speaker 36: sub stack about it. I've talked about it when I've been on various shows and so forth, but I haven't seen that really covered anyplace else. Have you? So that's like an actual something that could be represented into the public in a way that is rational and reasoned that actually would...
Speaker 36: be informative but it just doesn't get emphasized but what does get emphasized are these like fragments of like half a piece of some email somewhere that you can imbue with some salacious
Speaker 23: larger meaning and then people can like use that for
Speaker 10: their own like choose your own adventure quest where they're like everybody's like their own detective now where they're they're getting to the bottom of the pedophile conspiracy
um you
Speaker 10: know i think a reason why people also another element in terms of why people don't have the capacity to
Speaker 33: understand what is
Speaker 33: credible and what isn't in terms of how this stuff gets flushed out onto the internet especially is that because like when you get a screenshot of a document right and it's the fbi memorializing what like some mentally ill crank told them the fbi still memorializes that
just as
Speaker 23: a matter of course right without conferring any uh veracity to it
But
Speaker 23: when it comes out in
Speaker 36: this indiscriminate release of materials, it does look – it resembles like an officially looking document. Like it's got FBI letterhead. It's got like the stern looking typeface, right? It looks like something official and like almost super serious, right? So you could see some – like the untrained eye or the uninformed observer of this kind
Speaker 9: of just instinctively assuming that this must be like
–
real
Speaker 9: important serious info right um so i think that's actually an underrated aspect of how it is that some of
Speaker 10: the stuff gets almost assumed to be dispositive in terms of the allegations contained therein when it's hopefully definitely
Speaker 28: not before before we move on if it was in like if it was in like um a comic sans
Speaker 36: font and like in crayon or something like on the back of like a uh you know wendy's
Speaker 23: wrapper like it wouldn't it wouldn't confer the same like presumed credibility right but instead it's like FBI, wow, like this really stern,
Speaker 23: looking font
Speaker 10: and like it's got like it's written in a serious almost like uh rhetorical style and that's then there
you
Speaker 61: go i think that's an incredibly important point and that's a good way of putting uh the the point that i've been trying
to
Speaker 21: make about how we are misperceiving what's actually in this garbage dump before we move on to what's in the garbage dump and and some of the
Speaker 27: issues
that i
Speaker 27: think should have been raised that we're not just to for the record
Speaker 27: Michael Tracy, which story is more ridiculous or implausible, the dead girls at
Speaker 62: the New Mexico ranch story or the 1983 allegation against Donald Trump that he raped the teenager? Which one?
Well,
Speaker 33: just because it's possible that like some nut job in New Mexico might claim
Speaker 40: that they found like a skull of some sort of like, I don't know, 18th century bandit
Speaker 10: or something that like trekked across New Mexico.
i'm
Speaker 10: gonna go with the 1983 allegations against trump just because like what i mean it's amazing when people don't look into because like it's it's the same law firm lisa bloom was the daughter of gloria allred right who was responsible for this quote-unquote katie johnson lawsuit which you probably have heard of from 2016 and amazingly for the
record
Speaker 62: for the record as soon as glory allred's name even tangentially is involved in any story like this it's automatically bullcrap so just just for the record
i
Speaker 63: mean i think that's a probably a decent rule of thumb i don't know that
Speaker 40: i mean like in 100 of any and all cases like anything that gloria already comes in contact with is like 100 fabricated but
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): like yeah it's cause for some suspicion or skepticism sure
um and i asked
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): gloria already myself about her daughter's katie johnson uh lawsuit
and
Speaker 10: she refused to talk about it because she's like oh she's got her own clients i've got mine as if they don't like talk about it
Speaker 9: um
I
Speaker 64: totally get
Speaker 36: your answer. That Katie Johnson law from 2016 turned out to be a literal hoax, a literal fabrication that was ginned up by a former Jerry Springer show producer who did all these celebrity stunt things
Speaker 23: in Los Angeles where he's claiming, let's not get derailed into OJ, please, but he claimed that he sold drugs to OJ Simpson the day of the murders of Ron Goldman and Nicole Brown Simpson and stuff. And he just inserted himself with all these like crazy celebrity scandals as like a
Speaker 40: celebrity as like a stunt.
He
Speaker 40: was a professional like stuntman and hoax guy, right? Who would like then try to sell stuff to tabloids or whatever.
Speaker 9: Well, I'm glad that that was the firm that represented this woman who claims that Jeffrey Epstein in the 1980s for the first and only
Speaker 23: time that we ever know of, like took up residence in South Carolina. Really? What? And like also like plied her with drugs
Speaker 10: and alcohol, even though he was famously a teetotaler who like wouldn't
Speaker 40: even allow drugs or alcohol in his vicinity.
Speaker 40: And there's a million other crazy allegations
Speaker 65: to do with that. I'm glad that
Speaker 1: you and I, both who are not fans of Donald Trump, are in agreement of the absurdity with regard to the absurdity of the 1983 allegations.
Speaker 67: There's plenty of material that's actually true on Trump for us to be satisfied with. Like he's currently waging war in the Middle East in a crazy way. So if we had a
Speaker 65: competent media in
Speaker 69: general and specifically on this story,
I have
Speaker 65: seen some stuff in the files that
Speaker 27: should have happened.
Speaker 21: created a strong impetus to go back to the original narrative, the prism through which everyone sees this story and say, wait a minute. And specifically, I'm referring to what I think is one of the top three or four key narrative points in this entire fiasco. And I'm talking specifically about former Prince Andrew.
and um
Speaker 70: i refuse to say former prince i'm still going with prince if you want to sue me under british libel laws go ahead i will evoke the first amendment okay but he's still a prince in my eyes all
Speaker 72: right fine and and i don't think any of this should have happened to
Speaker 73: him and i think the epstein files depending on how you define files have proven his innocence one
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): of the most remarkable exchanges and i think i only saw this
I
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): forget. It might have been Time or Newsweek actually published this, but it's an extraordinary exchange. I'm sure you've seen it. Where Epstein
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): is emailing Andrew to tell him about Giuffre's allegation for the first time. You're getting his real life reaction to being accused in email. Oh, goodness me. What is this about?
And would
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): you agree that Andrew's reaction to Epstein telling him about this allegation is completely inconsistent with his guilt?
Speaker 76: And by the way, it's also completely inconsistent with Epstein believing that he's guilty. Do you agree with that?
yeah i
Speaker 70: think that's generally true i wouldn't therefore say it's necessarily unto itself dispositive i didn't say it was the positive i i
Speaker 77: said i but it's been almost completely ignored it would
Speaker 23: be consistent with him like having no clue what anybody's what they're even talking about and just like wanting to just be be apprised of what is even
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): true if it was true this is
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): private email they have absolutely no expectation will ever be made public in the future if it was true andrew would have said oh fuck what do i do that's what you would have said he didn't say that
Speaker 78: he had no understanding of what the hell epstein was even saying and then epstein makes a joke about a royal
Speaker 43: equivalent of saying oh fuck i'm not sure i'm trying to think like deary me
Speaker 79: well
Speaker 79: the reality is that no rational person can look at that exchange and at least not go, wait a minute, that points towards innocence, not towards guilt. And then there's the entire issue of Geoffrey's lack of credibility, which you have done a really good job on. It's probably worse. Her
Speaker 79: And the credibility of the reporter that vouched for her, Julie K. Brown, is probably even worse than I gave it credit for
Speaker 36: earlier on in this case. It's worse than you ever could have imagined. Like, it's worse than even I assume. Like, whenever I learn something additional, right, as
worse
Speaker 23: as I knew it to be, it always somehow gets exponentially even worse. It's like it's just staggering.
So
Speaker 80: tell me why. Tell me what you mean by that.
Speaker 23: Well...
How bad is
Speaker 61: the credibility of Geoffrey and Brown, the reporter from the Miami? I'll
Speaker 28: give you an example. Right. So the
origin of
Speaker 28: probably what the origin, if you could pinpoint the origin of the mythology to anything, as I see it,
it's this
Speaker 10: formative court filing from December 30th, 2014, right,
where.
So Bradley
Speaker 10: Edwards, who's still involved and was like conferring with Thomas Massey and O'Connor and drafting the Epstein Files Transparency Act
and is still
Speaker 10: involved in litigation with Bank of America to get a couple hundred more million dollars out of this. Right. So he's very much still an active player. And so to some extent is Paul Cassell. And they both brought this motion for Joinder on behalf of Virginia Roberts Gouffre, December 30th, 2014. And that's where all of the central planks of the mythology are essentially introduced because basically they just legitimize her position.
Speaker 10: alternate reality almost like semi psychotic sort of delusions right and then they
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): put into a court filing where it looks official right
and then
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): it's kind of like disseminated to the media strategically and the the the rationale for that as far as
I can
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): ascertain was that
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): They were trying to use that as a leverage that they could then cite
Speaker 23: to other potential targets for settlements that they wanted to go
Speaker 10: after, saying, look, if you don't pay up, your name could appear in one of these filings, too. So that probably is what happened with Wexner to some extent. I'm amazed that when Wexner did this deposition in Ohio a few weeks ago, nobody asked him, hey, did you ever settle?
did you
Speaker 10: ever make a settlement payment to Virginia Roberts Gouffre? Cause she had accused him of being one of the endless high profile or wealthy men who had sexually victimized her. Right. But then she kind of dropped the claim almost like without explanation after a
Speaker 23: while, but it's in the deposition at one point. But
in that motion for
Speaker 10: jointer, right. That's where she, that's where they introduced and I'm saying they mean this collective of Virginia Roberts Gouffre in concert with the profit seeking
lawyers and
And
Speaker 10: that's where they introduce
the claims
Speaker 10: of child sex crimes against Alan Dershowitz, Prince Andrew,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and John Luke Brunel, in
terms of
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): whose name specifically. They also name Maxwell and Epstein, obviously, but then they gesture towards other category of wrongdoers
Speaker 10: whom she was also trafficked to, like princes, prime ministers, foreign, blah, blah, blah, like
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): all kinds of prominent people who run the world, right? And then she says she believes that there's blackmail involved, right? So that gets introduced in this motion for Joinder.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): And,
you
Speaker 10: know, when I first
Speaker 23: sort of got started doing a deep dive on all this stuff, right, I I actually knew about the recantation of
Speaker 10: the Dershowitz claims I I knew about, you know, the trajectory of Andrew claims, but the thing with John Luke Brunel was always a little bit more of an enigma to
me.
And
Speaker 33: the John Luke Brunel kind of angle on all this is integral in why people have come to postulate that there's this sprawling international sex trafficking operation. Because this guy was like a modeling mogul of sorts in France who did have a relationship with Epstein, right?
Speaker 82: Do you believe
Speaker 83: that any of those three claims by
Speaker 84: Geoferi were-
I keep
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): becoming more and more amazed at the depths of this whole operation. Finally, I say
Speaker 23: to myself, this is maybe late December. I want to figure out how to do some kind of deep dive on John Luke Brunel
Speaker 10: because I don't want to come up empty when people ask me, what's the deal with John Luke Brunel? I knew some stuff, but not enough to really be fully conversant. So I'm starting to read French
Speaker 23: media, right? I got
to get
Speaker 23: it translated and everything.
And
Speaker 23: turns out when
Jean-Luc Brunel
Speaker 23: was arrested
Speaker 10: in 2019 under pressure from the U.S. after Epstein's arrest, right, because he was considered a potential co-conspirator, the French authorities do arrest him.
They put
Speaker 10: him in jail and he stays
in jail
Speaker 10: for like a year and a half until in 2021, the French authorities summoned Virginia Roberts
Speaker 23: Gouffre to come from Australia to give evidence against him in this distinctly French
Speaker 10: situation.
Speaker 10: pre-trial session where it's like the defense attorneys and the prosecutors are in a colloquy with virginia robert scuffray
um it
Speaker 45: doesn't exist in the american system and sure enough lo and behold she ends up retracting your claims
against him too and and it's
Speaker 85: just to be clear at times she has retracted her allegation against andrew or
Speaker 73: at least omitted it correct there have been times in which she has changed her mind about whether or not andrew abused her correct? She's
Speaker 45: attracted certain claims. The initial claim in 20,
Speaker 45: When Sharon Churcher of the Daily Mail went and interviewed her, at least in
Speaker 23: terms of how Sharon Churcher presents it in these series of articles that are like somewhat serialized, is
Speaker 33: that Sharon
Speaker 23: Churcher
says
Speaker 33: something to the effect of there's no claim that anything sexual happened between Virginia and Andrew, but they're putting out the story to just kind
of.
Speaker 33: Cause a stir because
Speaker 10: somebody who was apparently an Epstein in the orbit of this, you know, sex pest Epstein also
Speaker 33: liaised or interacted with or was present with Prince Andrew at some point. Like that was the that was the only allegation really in that initial story in 2011. But then the mythology kind of grows or intensifies or gets dramatized further as the
Speaker 87: years go by. But like she
Speaker 45: also.
Speaker 45: The key claims got retracted against this Jean-Luc Brunel, too, to the point that after she retracted him, Jean-Luc Brunel filed his own criminal complaint against her in Paris. So I've been trying to figure out I've been talking to French journalists who actually contact me and asking, look, look, I'm not an expert.
you know
Speaker 45: talk about expertise i'm definitely not an expert in french public records law so if anybody can figure out for god's sake how to get some information on this that's a little bit more comprehensive i would really appreciate it but like that's just another thing i was just taking for granted that got that was retracted but don't amazingly enough in that internet i'll tie it up here in that international best-selling quote-unquote
Speaker 33: memoir that was put out under her name last october nobody's girl virginia robert scuffray top of the amazon
charts
the
Speaker 87: United States in Britain in Australia etc wall-to-wall hyper credulous media coverage everywhere
you look it open
Speaker 36: the fit the book opens with like an opening anecdote where she's taking this like contemplative stroll through the pizzas streets of Paris and admiring the
Woman 58: architecture and the beauty of the city and it's when she's there to give evidence against Jean-Luc Brunel that she had to retract that's the
Speaker 86: opening anecdote of this
book
Speaker 88: Well, the problems with the book, I'm
Speaker 89: fascinated by
Speaker 88: the
Speaker 73: fact that we've just pretended that she didn't kill herself just before
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): releasing a book. I mean, I'm sorry, that matters. When you, I mean, you're rich, you're famous, you have a fan club, the media loves you, you're years and years away from this alleged horrendous abuse you suffered. You kill yourself literally right Right before releasing a book,
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): That's a problem
Speaker 90: that should at least raise questions, especially when in the book you don't name any names. You make more allegations. You know,
Speaker 51: some, you know, which names she names or, you know, which names the publisher authorizes being named in that book names of
Speaker 37: people
Speaker 23: who are deceased.
Speaker 37: Right. Of course, because they can't sue the
Speaker 91: name Bill Richardson, who was the former Democratic presidential candidate, New Mexico governor, the name Marvin Minsky, the MIT professor who's dead. They're both dead.
Speaker 48: Right. But here's the supposed prime minister who violently raped her aboard a plane. Well, I want to get to
Speaker 92: the that to me is the smoking gun. The prime
Speaker 53: minister story is the smoking gun that the media doesn't really believe her because
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): here she is the star of this entire saga. Right. Right.
so
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): much of this rides on her. And she writes in the book, the only thing that's new in the public consciousness of any significance is that there's a prime minister who raped her.
How
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): come there has not been any effort to track down who the hell this prime minister is? I mean, with all the witch hunt going on in this story, nobody seems to care to try to
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): figure out who the prime minister is. Why? Because no one really believes there's a prime minister, Michael.
It
Speaker 23: was assumed, like on social
media,
Speaker 23: media to be ehud barack the former israeli prime minister and maybe that is who she's
Speaker 15: alleging did that i don't know um but there's been no effort to try to pressure barack met ehud
Speaker 10: barack as far as i know did not
even meet
Speaker 10: epstein until after 2002 which is when virginia robert scuffray you know fled to thailand because she had to warrant for her arrest in
Speaker 93: florida
Speaker 94: are you are you understanding of
Speaker 93: course yeah yeah yeah so but the and you know what the rationalization for that is like why she didn't name the person
Speaker 23: and i tried to ask the ghostwriter
Speaker 10: amy wallace
Speaker 10: this question when I was on Piers Morgan last October before the latest fiasco.
And it
Speaker 10: was a
Speaker 39: segment where Piers interviews Amy Wallace, the ghostwriter of the book, and then they bring
on
Speaker 60: a panel, right? She's awful. So I thought I was going to have a direct maybe exchange with her, but unfortunately I didn't. And the rationalization is that for Judy Roberts, she was
Speaker 95: scared for her safety.
That's why she didn't name
Speaker 95: this prime minister. It's just like you've named like a billion other people who could –
In
Speaker 95: theory, compromise your safety, but then that feeds into this perception that, oh, maybe she was killed last April when she was reported dead, right? She was not. And she – but another thing about Virginia Robertson Fair that's worth underscoring is like, first of all, I mean I think if you had
to –
Like for a
Speaker 96: while, I kind of hedged on whether I would even just conceive that she was dead just because I hadn't gotten any additional like materials that would corroborate that from the Australian government.
And I
Speaker 96: tried now,
like
Speaker 40: there's enough progress in the probate court, like over her estate. It's very lucrative, like, you know, tens of billions of dollars that, you know, I'm willing to stipulate that she's deceased at this point. OK, she's got like Tom Sawyer in the
Speaker 95: rafters looking down on his funeral. But like she, you know, she had just had the custody of her children.
Speaker 45: rescinded from her by the Australian Child Welfare Authorities
Speaker 85: and given to the husband. The other smoking gun is, where's her husband? Where's her
Speaker 98: husband? How about this, John? How about this, John? You're
Speaker 36: going to talk about her
Speaker 99: brother, right? The brother and the dad. I'm
Speaker 36: not. So she had made variations of the Prime Minister claim in the past. She filled it in with a lot more vivid detail in the new book, to sell books, right? But what
Speaker 36: new claim she did introduce was that among you know the endless you know cycle of men that culminated in her husband that she claimed that she was abused by it all started when she was
molested by
Speaker 36: her father which would have been pedophilic molestation at the time right at the age she said that she was molested by her father so why haven't her siblings who are on the media constantly giving these tearful interviews or like speaking to congress they were just at the Zorro Ranch this past
Speaker 45: weekend. Why haven't they demanded
a
Speaker 45: criminal investigation of the father right he's still alive he's still around no
Speaker 100: sense it's
Speaker 21: absolutely absurd now with regard to andrew i think andrew is the linchpin of this whole thing i i think if andrew doesn't fall um that there's a good chance this story is not being talked about today because it it really created the avalanche it created the perception of this narrative of all these powerful people that were involved in a sex trafficking ring it provided maca world with that is,
Speaker 21: that they were going to see this public execution of more elites, because that's what MAGA really desires. And I have come to believe, for a lot of different reasons, partially because of your work, that Prince Andrew was innocent. And is it possible they
Speaker 65: had some sort of romantic or sexual contact? Yeah, I guess that's possible,
Speaker 63: but he never sexually...
right i mean
Speaker 65: like even if
Speaker 23: they did like hypothetically even if that she he and virginia robertson fray did have some kind of sexual
encounter she
Speaker 23: would have been 17 at the time which is a year above the legal age of consent in england right so i don't know how that could be pedophilia unless you're saying that in england the state authorizes rampant
Speaker 39: pedophilic predation i mean there's state sanctioned pedophilia right now in england
Speaker 81: but michael i want to
Get
Speaker 81: your opinion on something we talked about when we agreed to do this second
Speaker 21: interview together, because I've been trying to make the case to you that this case has a lot of similarities to the Penn State Sandusky case, especially when it comes to the settlement process, and that Andrew, I think, has a lot of similarities to the
Penn State.
um
Speaker 21: psychologically as well as some other elements of his story to jerry sandusky including the fact that i believe them both to be totally innocent of criminal allegations
Speaker 102: can you give me your current opinion on on my analysis there do you see the parallels i mean
i see the
Speaker 9: parallel that you're trying to sketch out i don't know that it's the most illuminating
Speaker 10: parallel necessarily that i would come up with i mean
I
Speaker 10: think it's hard to analogize Prince Andrew to a Penn State football coach
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): just because the social stratum in which Prince Andrew existed or exists. But in the smaller world, Michael,
Speaker 104: it's exactly the same. So incomparable to anything else, given the peculiarities of the royal family. In the world of State College, Sandusky was in an incredibly similar position. They both gave horrendous
Speaker 21: interviews or perceived to be horrendous interviews Yeah, that's true. To bias...
Speaker 21: media outlets um that created the perception of their guilt and most importantly this is this is and i've sent you information on this i don't know you've been too busy to take a look at it penn state and the royal family acted exactly
in
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): the same way when it came to paying off false accusations okay yeah no evidence in an effort to try to get a story past them money that they didn't really need. In the case of Penn State, it's not their money.
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): The royal family has got more money than they know what to do with. And they make a deal thinking it's going to go away when, in fact, it gets perceived as a guilty plea on behalf of someone who never pleaded guilty. Sandusky never pleaded guilty. Andrew never pleaded guilty. Do you see that parallel? No,
Speaker 109: that's that's not parallel for sure. After
Speaker 10: Andrew was arrested a few weeks ago on this trumped up public misconduct charge, which is just like a catch all that could mean anything pretty much as far as I understand it in
terms of that.
the
Speaker 10: statute in england right um meaning
it was just
Speaker 10: basically a pretext for them to dole out some measure of punishment against him for the perceived sex crime right
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): which
they
Speaker 10: couldn't
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): prove or bring any sort of formal charge in relation to so they whipped up this thing about oh when he was like the informal trade envoy in the 2000s he sent some email to epstein which were like totally unremarkable emails that no one would give like a second thought to if they weren't tied to jeffrey Epstein, the most notorious pedophile and like
Speaker 23: all
the rest of
Speaker 23: mythology right um
but yeah i mean
Speaker 23: the british royal family i've been saying is just like has been totally feckless in their handling of this i'm curious contrast the british royal family's treatment of any allegations against them with the allegation how trump treats them like trump could not be more abrasively dismissive right in terms of his own culpability in anything he calls it a hoax etc whereas the british royal family they they make a
Speaker 36: point in terms of their whoever's
To
Speaker 36: constantly make concessions that they think are going to put a stop to the uproar or somehow tamp down the uproar, but only end up feeding it further because you're seeming to give credence to the premises of those allegations time and time again. Yes, the settlement,
over the
Speaker 9: course of that settlement, they thought, hey, this is going to cover our bases here. It's going to finally put a...
But it put a
Speaker 23: stop to all this furor because in the settlement money that were given to Virginia Roberts Gouffre by way of David
Speaker 10: Boies et al, her lawyers, we're going to earmark a portion of it for this sex trafficking awareness organization that Virginia Roberts Gouffre had established in her name nominally by Edwards and friends that was supposed to be like based in Australia, but it was based in Florida. I mean, it's a whole like it didn't register with the IRS like it was it was delinquent on its IRS registration a year.
Speaker 33: After the 2.7 million got dispersed into the accounts for this phony organization, right? And she was just like a professional victim. So which I, and I'm not even saying that to be pejorative. Like that's how her job title was described because they, they figured they would make up this entity for her called victims refuse silence. And then it got rebranded to receive the Andrews settlement later.
Speaker 33: And that was her livelihood, right? Because that was what she did. She tried to extract the biggest possible settlement that would enrich her lawyers, enrich herself, and then she could claim that she's an activist for sex trafficking awareness. So on her death, I mean, if that's like your mind frame, right? Like when you're just a permanent lifelong victim based on something that happened when you were maybe 17, 18, and 19,
I can
Speaker 33: see how that might happen.
Speaker 33: cause you to have like some longstanding mental issues that could get triggered if like something else goes wrong in your life and your children are taken away uh etc but like yeah but the parallel you're trying to draw there in terms of the more narrow one i'm not so into like the british royal family psychodrama with the king and the brother and everything but like in terms of how foolish it was for them to think that they could stamp this
thing out by just
Speaker 33: like you know
Speaker 10: giving some money
and then
Speaker 10: everybody can move
on
that was a
Speaker 10: nightmare that was nightmarishly bad pr advice and yeah it did feed into this larger perception
Speaker 23: about the epstein mythology writ large that there must be this there must be something vindicated about its
truth
Speaker 36: value right um right and you know and and ironically enough like it could lead to the downfall of the royal family itself in a sense because like
Speaker 23: they're going wild in britain over this it's almost as bad if not worse than in the united states
Speaker 12: yeah okay so i I think we're generally in agreement on Andrew
Speaker 12: And Jouffre's suicide, I think, has
Speaker 21: been completely underreported. Most people don't even know that she killed herself. And I think it's relevant for interpreting both her life
Speaker 2: as well as her book. But I got to ask
Speaker 35: you about. Virginia Robert Jouffre endorsed Donald Trump in the 2024 election. I
swear to God,
Speaker 9: it's true. And she also exchanged personal messages with, guess who? That's right, Elon Musk.
Speaker 9: that's great
Speaker 45: so she thought that she was like and because she had she had
Speaker 23: advocated like q anon theories in the past where like donald trump is this mythical superhero who's going to be taking on the pedo cabals so virginia robertsbury signed on
Speaker 45: to that like that was her mindset right and she was talking
and like
Speaker 45: elon musk is telling her like look you
Woman 58: know we're going to get the client list for you i'd forget i felt i forget exactly what was said between them in a d in a twitter i think i think
Speaker 111: she was mentally ill and
Speaker 62: obviously she was mentally ill she ended up killing herself under circumstances
that would not
Speaker 62: How funny is it that she endorsed Trump? It's amazing. But I want to go from her suicide
Speaker 112: to Epstein's suicide. And part of
Speaker 113: the parameters for this interview. I mean, maybe
Speaker 70: we should just bracket this because I've never seen somebody get so beet
Speaker 96: red.
Speaker 96: OK, and scream at such an intensity on a stream as you
did the
Speaker 96: last time we talked about
Speaker 112: full disclosure. In order to get you to agree to this interview, I promised you that I would
Speaker 21: not yell at you in general and specifically not on the suicide issue. And I will keep that promise, even though you've claimed that you don't think I can keep that promise. I will. I promise you. OK, I don't make promises. I can't.
Speaker 21: I don't make promises I can't keep,
but I
Speaker 21: have to at least address the suicide issue with you because it's been a topic in the news quite a bit because of stray fragments in the Epstein files being pieced together by the Epstein didn't kill himself conspiracy nuts into trying to without actually creating an alternative scenario or a theory, just simply
Speaker 21: Asking questions about the convention of wisdom that the authorities determined and Dan Bongino agreed with and Cash Patel agreed with. Oh, Dan Bongino. I mean, I don't I can't think who's a more unblemished
Speaker 114: with and the medical examiner agreed with that that he actually did kill himself
Speaker 2: to the autopsy.
I'm
Speaker 2: telling you all the people that have said publicly that he killed himself.
Speaker 39: Saying Dan Bongino said something does not give me any confidence whatsoever.
Speaker 21: You have to understand that he has a self-interest. He had previously been very much on the Epstein didn't kill himself train. And so therefore it's an admission against self-interest as
Speaker 115: – and it just happened to coincide with him getting full information as deputy director.
Speaker 116: In other words, Dan Bongino would have loved to have –
Speaker 116: told his MAGA social media followers, look, Cash
Speaker 9: and I, we sparrow into office to fight the deep state, and we're going to finally unveil the truth to you about Epstein not killing himself. Exactly. That's true. All
Speaker 72: right. Now,
Speaker 21: is there anything in the Epstein files? Because it's my view that all these stories related to the
Speaker 27: suicide, if you actually dig even a little bit and you use your brain a little bit, there's still...
Speaker 27: Far, far more
Speaker 21: consistent with suicide than they are with some sort of murder. Now, is it possible, underline possible, and I've always said this is the case, is it possible that the guards were paid off to look the
Speaker 27: other way or for some reason? Bingo. But that's still a suicide. But that's still
Speaker 117: a suicide. All I'm saying
is.
Speaker 117: okay go ahead finish your question
Speaker 118: no i mean that my question my question is is there anything in the most recent revelations that
Speaker 21: you believe is credible evidence that epstein killed himself i
mean or i'll give you
Speaker 119: one example
i
Speaker 81: read let me let me hold on i'm sorry let me let me let me rephrase that is there anything in the most recent epstein files revelations that you think is credible evidence
that he was murdered okay okay
So let
Speaker 28: me just stipulate that all I've ever said about this is that in contrast with virtually
Speaker 10: every other aspect of this sprawling, multifaceted issue, my
only point
Speaker 10: has been that as to the death in August of 2019 at the Manhattan Federal Detention Facility,
my view
Speaker 10: is that there is more reasonable doubt as to the manner
Speaker 23: of that death
happened.
Speaker 23: then there is reasonable doubt as to other dimensions of the story. That's my only point. Okay. And so I'll give you an example. I
Speaker 10: happen to read. And also, did you know, by the way, that Thomas Massey, you know, it was like the big champion
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): of Epstein files and like is just, you know, I'm denouncing everybody who's in the files, quote unquote, and calling for arrest of people. He
went out
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): and never specify. Although, you know,
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): He finally did specify a handful of them while he was under the protections of the speech and debate clause on the floor of the U.S. House of Representatives. He was on some podcast last
month saying
Speaker 10: his view is that Epstein is not even dead at all, that he was spirited out
of the
Speaker 10: jail. OK, well, then he still walks among us somewhere, whether it's Israel, whether it's
Speaker 120: not anywhere. That's crazy. But can you please? I want to know if he's such
Speaker 121: an expert on the Epstein files. Right. You can actually find photos of Epstein's body
Speaker 45: corpse on the stretcher.
Speaker 45: right in that you know in the hours after his uh death but and mike
Speaker 10: unless you can give me an explanation for why it's a body
Speaker 82: double or a fake body or something then how could you just go around i agree
with
Speaker 123: you on that give me give me give me the piece of information you think that has come
out if there is any
Speaker 123: that you think that's come out recently that indicates that
Speaker 124: epstein might have been
murdered
Speaker 91: okay
So
Speaker 10: I'll give you an example of something I read a few days ago. This was the New York city pathologist who was the pathologist on duty that day and called in to perform the examination of his body. And I'm not,
Speaker 23: you know, you know, hold your horses. I'm not saying that this proves anything in one way or another. Okay. I'm
just asking. And
Speaker 10: she's interviewed by a DOJ investigator.
Maybe
Speaker 10: it's Bureau of Prisons, a DOJ investigator looking into, they're doing an investigation on the circumstances of Epstein's death. And this woman is interviewed, she was then the New York City pathologist, she was interviewed in 2022. Now she is very unequivocal that she thinks that the only biological explanation for the injuries that she saw in terms of how the death came about was through suicide. So she's adamant about that. She doesn't waver on that. But then something a little bit odd happens where
Speaker 10: She's shown photographs of, like, the cell, right?
And at
Speaker 10: the time, like, the ligature
Speaker 23: that was seemingly used by Epstein to commit the suicide was supposed to have been delivered to her
when she's
Speaker 23: doing the autopsy or doing the examination
Speaker 10: so that she can, like, connect the particular device or not device exactly, but the noose that was created and,
Speaker 9: you know, correlate that with the injuries, right? And then she's, so she's presented with these photos and she
said,
So, wait,
Speaker 9: they
Speaker 45: gave me a different ligature. What happened was that the prison staff, they delivered to her something that she then inferred years after the fact was not actually the ligature that Epstein used to commit what she still presumed and concluded was a suicide,
but...
It was
Speaker 45: still like you could see and see her and this DOJ investigator sort of puzzling over what the heck happened
Speaker 33: because they show her some other ligature that was in the cell that probably was the more likely one that was used by upstate. OK, so I'm not saying that proves something one way or another.
Speaker 33: I'm just saying that I have a little bit – I have more
Speaker 45: epistemic humility,
Speaker 23: okay, as to the death
than any
Speaker 23: other dimension of this. And I know that you're very commendably trying to contain your anger right now, but that's
my
Speaker 33: position. That said, if you ask me, gun to my head, was it a suicide or homicide, I would say suicide. All I'm saying is that my confidence interval is
lower –
on the
Speaker 33: question of
Speaker 125 (lower-pitched voice): the death than it is on other dimensions of the story. And
I
Speaker 112: will say two things. First of all, I appreciate you answering the question. Second, I'll say two things.
Speaker 126 (lower-pitched voice): Michael, what
you just
Speaker 126 (lower-pitched voice): suggested there to me is not remotely...
Speaker 126 (lower-pitched voice): I'm not trying to convince you that it was – I didn't present that as intended to be convincing proof that it was a homicide. No, hold on. But if you let me – please let me finish
Speaker 53: my comment slash question because I don't think you're fully thinking about this in the context of a case that is now seven years old almost where we have had unprecedented cases.
Speaker 53: Investigation and disclosure, unprecedented investigation and disclosure, unprecedented public interest with people having a huge self-interest in proving he was murdered. And yet, despite all that, seven years later, that's the best that the pro-murder people have got.
I
Speaker 53: mean, come on.
Speaker 118: I'm
not a
Speaker 118: pro-murder person. I just happen to be looking through this particular document.
But
Speaker 30: Michael, I think that's – to me, this is a classic case.
Speaker 95: Oh, and actually, you know what the pathologist also says in that exchange with
Speaker 33: the DOJ investigator? That she sort of did almost enhance protocols for the examination because
–
Speaker 33: she reasons that
Speaker 46: Epstein might be somebody would be somebody that people, people would want dead. Something to that effect.
Speaker 129: Right. Again, it doesn't prove anything, which goes to
Speaker 46: her credibility. She just like
Speaker 130: did additional protocols. Yeah. That goes to her credibility and the credibility of her conclusion. But sure. I, I, I, to me, this whole suicide situation is
Speaker 53: almost the perfect example of where the absence of evidence is evidence of absence, because if he was murdered by this point,
Speaker 53: We would have overwhelming evidence to that effect, including, by the way, we would have a suspect because it's impossible to get into a federal prison and
not be
Speaker 130: caught killing
Speaker 131: somebody. Well, nobody had to get into it necessarily. There's a scenario where it
Speaker 132: could have been another
Speaker 131: inmate and they do a low-level
Speaker 133: conspiracy with the guards and something like that. Michael, we have a very, very limited – It didn't have to be a Mossad, Clinton,
Speaker 1: Trump infiltration. You have a very limited number of people whose names we all have who
would have actually
Speaker 1: had access you don't have
Speaker 134: all the names of the inmates that were on the block or in the jail that uh michael okay we don't john but michael here's i go
Speaker 135: where the evidence leads well the evidence here is overwhelming but here's the evidence leads me to at
Speaker 52: least to just a concession to some measure of reasonable doubt i don't think it's not unreasonable
Speaker 81: but michael here's the more important part
i think
Speaker 21: you completely misunderstood my anger
the
Speaker 21: last time we talked about this i cried all night that night i'm sure you did but this is in all sincerity yes i'm irritated that a guy i respect and think is a smart is not willing to say what i believe very strongly to be the obvious truth of this that's irritating
Speaker 136: but the reason why i got angry here's why i got angry michael i know
the
Speaker 136: way the media works. I know the way these conspiracy theorists. And what's Sarah Palin up to?
Speaker 53: Yeah, I understand. Even though you know the details of this case
Speaker 21: better than I do, I understand the dynamics of it in a bigger picture, probably more than anybody else does, partially because of my experience with Sandusky. But that's not just it. It's my I understand the
Speaker 136: way these things go down. And to me,
By
Speaker 136: allowing the idea that Epstein might have been murdered to gain traction or maintain traction, it opens up all the conspiracy doors or windows. If it was ever accepted that Epstein committed suicide, which he did, it would simultaneously close
Speaker 53: off the,
so
Speaker 53: many of these ridiculous stories and because it has not been closed off your job is impossible okay that was partially why i was being i was getting upset at you because you your position makes it impossible to close off all the conspiracy doors because if he was murdered it imbues this case with magical powers because if they can kill him in a federal perspective
Speaker 53: prison and not have anyone be charged. My God, these people are powerful. My God, they must run the world. My God,
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): the incentive to kill him. By the way, for some reason, Ghislaine Maxwell was never killed, which doesn't make any goddamn sense. But the incentive to kill him must have been so huge that there must really be something to these incredibly ridiculous, massive conspiracy theories. Do you
Speaker 53: not at least acknowledge...
Do
Speaker 53: you just acknowledge that I'm right about the fact
Speaker 137: that the perception he was murdered is key to people believing lots of things that are not true? I
mean, I accept your
Speaker 138: statement. I don't know what to
tell you.
OK, but
Speaker 138: that's from from the standpoint of I didn't go into
Speaker 36: this thinking, OK, I'm I'm like almost doing a counter propaganda thing where all the conspiracy adjacent
Speaker 10: people are into every possible maximalist conspiratorial interpretation of everything. Therefore, my job is to be the anti conspiracy guy and have that as my foregone conclusion or presupposition.
Speaker 10: and go into every little nook and cranny here with an eye toward closing the door to any possible conspiratorial
Speaker 96: interpretation. Like, that's not the approach that I took. I kind of started from scratch on every aspect of the Epstein story.
I
Speaker 139: get it,
and I
Speaker 139: respect that.
I
Speaker 140: get that and respect that, but from a strategic standpoint, not to mention that I believe.
You
Speaker 9: know, I'm not like sitting around strategizing, okay? I mean, my strategy is I follow my intuitions and then let the chips fall where they may. All
Speaker 81: right, let me, all right.
Speaker 81: I'm going to, I'm going to table that by the way. Did I, did I adhere to my promise to you? Yes. Well
Speaker 141: done, John.
I
Speaker 21: know that was difficult for you. All right. Let me finish up. Cause you've been generous with your time and I appreciate that, but I want to ask you a personal question. Cause I have
no
Speaker 111: connection to this case. I've been talking about it on my podcast and tweeting about it, but it has really depressed me.
Speaker 136: Um, I, I,
Speaker 136: I have a very dim view of the media and the public,
but even I
Speaker 136: have been, I have been very, even I have been stunned by just how stupid the media and the public has been in buying so many of these
Speaker 21: obviously ridiculous stories to the point where I became very despondent a couple of weeks ago. Like I mean, more despondent than I've been in years, even on the Sandusky story.
Speaker 142: John, I didn't know you'd been going through such hard times. I
Speaker 21: would have consoled you since you've been involved in it deeply
and
Speaker 21: and and you know been much more public about it and doing all these interviews and and being written about and whatever has this been a a negative experience in your life i know you've been wrongly accused of being paid
Speaker 65: because that's exactly what the people who are in opposition of the contrarians always say when they can't fight you on the facts they say oh someone mysterious is paying them which of course is utterly ridiculous in the case of
Speaker 143: both of us but how has this been for you personally i wish i was being
Speaker 144: paid by these mysterious billionaires so i I could get a better...
Speaker 144: Probably move out of this apartment. How has the story
Speaker 145: been for you personally in fighting this fight?
Speaker 23: Yeah, you know, I haven't been depressed by it really, interestingly enough. And if anything, I find that I'm invigorated by it because there's such. Well, good for you. There's such a wealth of material.
It's
Speaker 10: such an amazing story on so many levels in terms of the perspective
Speaker 60: that I take on it, right, as a moral panic, as a mass hysteria, as this like internationalized, all-consuming mega narrative that, oh, by the way, is also the dominant anti-Trump narrative of the second term, but like it's not limited to Trump.
Speaker 10: It's got, I learned something new almost every day, like you'd be amazed at the international correspondence that
I get from places
Speaker 10: that, you know, are so far afield from what people in the United States even conceive as even being relevant to Epstein,
right?
um so in
Speaker 23: a way i
find it
Speaker 23: almost like like i said almost invigorating because it's an amazing story i mean i think it's like an era almost to find like jeffrey
Speaker 125 (lower-pitched voice): epstein's like a world historic figure now as bizarrely as that sounds um all
Speaker 146: right well
Speaker 36: i'm glad i'm sort of uh i'm sort of i have a drive toward doing what i can to try
to
And
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): chronicle it and synthesize it and, you know, preserve
Speaker 147: it for like the historical record on some level. Because it's like it goes well, because like, I mean, look, I
Speaker 23: mean, people, the internet, millions upon millions of people are convinced that there's a war in the middle or east right now that's being waged to protect pedophiles.
Like
Speaker 23: that's how all consuming this thing has gotten. That's how many, that's how, that's how far its tentacles go. And to me, that's incredible. Isn't that amazing? Like it's just like on its face, an amazing
Speaker 81: story. It's amazing, but it's also depressing
Speaker 21: because to me, and I hate conspiracy theories, but each crazy conspiracy theory makes it easier for the next crazy conspiracy theory to be embraced. We've already talked about the fact that this is the first one that I think the mainstream news media has wholesale bought in on.
uh
Speaker 21: for for unique reasons and to
me i
Speaker 21: just see this as a downward spiral that's never going to end there's going to be some something crazier than this uh as long as it it makes people feel good about themselves by the way this is i have two very quick questions this one's a little bit off the wall but in trying to come up with an explanation for why there's so many people obsessed with this case
Speaker 21: And I was very hesitant to come to this conclusion, Michael, but I believe that I don't know what the percentage is. It's not a
Speaker 27: majority, but there is a percentage of people who are so willing to believe that all these rich, powerful people are
Speaker 53: pedophiles that it makes me think.
that
Speaker 53: there must be some sort of pedophilic tendencies in themselves. If they really truly believe that this is that common and that they're kind of hoping
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): for these videos and pictures and the Epstein files to finally give us the goods. Do you think there's anything to that? I
don't know that
Speaker 10: I would quite go there in terms of like a general prog prognosis in terms of what people are motivated by on this thing. I think that there's,
some
Speaker 10: sort of like perverse psychic gratification that people get from assuming that anybody that they might not like for any any other
reason is
Speaker 10: therefore also some sort of depraved sex criminal and all the better if they're a pedophilic sex criminal because that makes them the worst possible
Speaker 9: thing
Speaker 150: anybody could be i'm sure there's like there's
Speaker 63: something almost like entertaining people get like entertainment out of it well they
Speaker 53: want they want the public execution of elites that's and that's that's my last question one of the most bizarre things i've ever seen
Speaker 53: in politics is
Speaker 152: that but people you could pull up videos of these like vigilante pedo hundred guys who like they'll they'll basically
Speaker 95: entrap some walmart worker and then go kick his ass if they if he
was you
Speaker 95: know messaging on some app with a decoy who was like 15 or something okay like meaning an adult but they play pretend that they're a decoy and then they get one of these like you know guys who are nobodies involved in some kind of like sexually suggestive I mean, this is like hugely popular on the internet.
I
Speaker 95: mean, there's like, there's guys who do that for a living. I had one of them, one of them debate, I had a debate set up with me where like his full time job is to go around the United States and he has his staff or his people or whatever, get on these apps and
Speaker 60: present as, you know, 13, 14, 15 year old girls. And then they
go.
you
Speaker 60: know, nail the guy and they show up and they confront him sometimes. I don't
Speaker 23: think this guy beats their ass, but like other guys do. And then they get the police involved and they think that in their pedo hunters, I mean, I'm telling you this stuff is popular. So it's not just solely about wanting to take down a lane. Obviously that's a component,
but it's
Speaker 33: something that is unique to the viscerality of this anti pedo preoccupation such that last weekend we had a nationwide day of mobilization where the anti pedo protesters were,
went
Speaker 33: out around the country
Speaker 23: and sang songs and chanted for punishment of pedos as though they're not already the most criminalized like demographic in the country by
Speaker 33: far. So there's something unique to that. And then like, but like there's so many layers to the mythology that it all kind of coalesces together. And it gives you like the perfect recipe for something that people are fixated on. You have like this choose your own adventure thing where everybody can become their own detective. Cause there's so many files. Now you have like now these extra layers of like,
Speaker 33: Cannibalism that people want to impute and satanic ritual sacrifice. So there's like a demonological element. You have the intelligence aspect where people who are already like myopically fixated on Israel, they can tie in Israel
to it.
You
Speaker 10: have this more female-coded thing. I just posted a segment from The View yesterday where it's definitely an insight into what tends to be the more female-coded sort of understanding of Epstein and why it resonates with them, which is why it's like women who are going through their own therapy journeys and their trauma and therefore wanting to show their solidarity with the Epstein survivors, etc.,
Speaker 10: So like you can like it's got something for everyone. It's got something for
Speaker 23: each sex in terms of like, you know, general sex related sort of interests or tendencies. It's got something for everybody in like who's got some kind of pre-existing political grudge against the British royal family, against some businessman
Speaker 10: in the United Arab Emirates, against Putin, against whomever.
Speaker 10: there's like something for everyone, almost literally. So that's why, that's what makes this so singular and why I almost am a little bit resistant to try to analogize it to other stuff. Because I really think it stands apart in the annals of like mass
Speaker 125 (lower-pitched voice): manias that we have been subject
to as a
Speaker 125 (lower-pitched voice): civilization. Well,
Speaker 153: I'm glad
Speaker 112: you're amused by it. I'm more depressed by it, but I'm trying to become amused by it. But last, since I already
Speaker 21: referenced this last question with MAGA,
Speaker 21: Most crazy – the craziest thing I've ever seen in politics might be that this story really
Speaker 1: became a story because of MAGA, in my view, wanting the execution of elites in a public forum, even though Donald Trump was president.
Speaker 43: Specifically Democratic elites or like perceived Democratic-aligned elites or liberal elites. I don't
Speaker 155: know that they give a shit. I don't think that they care. Donald Trump's an elite. They don't want him executed, do they? No, but hold on a second.
If
Speaker 155: you let me finish my closer relationship with Epstein than like Bill Clinton. That's why it's
Speaker 156 (higher-pitched voice): so bizarre, is that
Speaker 155: why would
Speaker 156 (higher-pitched voice): MAGA pick a story
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): involving Jeffrey Epstein? I'll tell you why. Clearly, very closely tied to their hero, Donald Trump, and who killed himself in a federal prison under the authority of Donald Trump's attorney general, Bill Barr.
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): And and then.
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): We have this incredibly strange situation where the people really pushing this, especially in Congress right now, are almost all the most Trumpy of Republican
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): women, along with Thomas Massey. I guess you would
Speaker 65: still call him a Republican, a
guy I
Speaker 65: used to have a lot of respect for, but I think he's completely lost his shit. I think he's jumped the shark in an enormous way. It's embarrassing.
Speaker 65: Do you
Speaker 79: find it, what is your explanation for how it is that it is
Speaker 74 (higher-pitched voice): Republican lawmakers that are leading the charge on this when it clearly hurts Trump and it would require a conspiracy, what they're saying would require a conspiracy involving Donald
Speaker 157: Trump, involving Pam Bondi, involving Cash Patel, involving Dan Bongino. How does this make any sense?
Yeah, I
Speaker 15: mean, it's amazing. And not just the most
Speaker 10: hardcore, addled, almost like crazed people like a Nancy Mace or a Lauren Boebert or a Marjorie Taylor Greene, who's now out of Congress, but like people of that ilk. But
I just
Speaker 10: saw recently there was a more kind of conventional, almost
Speaker 9: somewhat quote unquote normie Republicans, Eric
Speaker 96: Burleson. I think he attended the Clinton deposition that
they did
Speaker 96: two weeks ago, where even he is now coming out like recently and saying that.
I've
Speaker 96: done it. I want to let everybody know that I just completed a in-depth study of the Epstein files, and I'm incredibly concerned that Leslie Wexner and Leon Black have not been charged, and I'm going to be advocating now for some kind of action. And this is not somebody who you would have even
Speaker 60: associated with that other kind
of MAGA sort
Speaker 60: of hallucinatory group. This is more of just like a conventional Republican guy.
Speaker 60: so but I think in terms
Speaker 33: of so there is sort of like a MAGA variance of the common mythology that I think explains why it is that people of that inclination did get so invested in the story
Speaker 95: and in that MAGA variation Donald Trump is the hero Donald Trump is the guy who
you
Speaker 46: know threw Epstein out of Mar-a-Lago like that was just like some claim that got invented and then was assumed true even though there was really never any basis for it right but like the idea was that Donald Trump had this
Speaker 46: amazing foresight to recognize what a predatory threat Epstein was and like throw him to the wolves and kick him out of Mar-a-Lago, even though Virginia Roberts Gouffre was the spa attendant at Mar-a-Lago and got trafficked out of there, quote unquote by Ghislaine, supposedly according to like the main, the mainline narrative. But Donald again, but Donald Trump was actually, it gets to like how the Q stuff developed or enveloped Donald Trump.
He was
Speaker 46: the one who was like, he was heroically being sent into the belly of the beast
and,
Speaker 46: right, to root out the pedophilic corruption, and so that kind of transferred over onto his supposed
role in
Speaker 46: the EPSU thing, it just never made
Speaker 33: any sense I was on this rumble debate
Speaker 23: or stream with this guy Vivo who's
like a
Speaker 23: big Trump guy and
And
Speaker 23: he was just adamant to me because I told him, look, I'm not trying to make a partisan point, I promise. But if you were to compare and
Speaker 10: contrast the longevity and the intricacy of the relationship between Jeffrey Epstein and Bill Clinton and Jeffrey Epstein and Donald Trump
–
No
Speaker 10: contest. Donald Trump and Epstein had a much longer term and much more elaborate relationship. Bill Clinton only really even interacted with them because of Ghislaine Maxwell as a conduit and definitely wasn't showing up to the Palm Beach house for dinner, as we have seen for some of these files, or like leaving message pads with Donald Trump written on it. Or even like one of the victims, alleged government victims in the Ghislaine Maxwell trial, Nadia Björlund, who was
a Days
Speaker 10: of Our Lives actress.
She
Speaker 9: says, and I think this is probably right,
Ghislaine.
Speaker 9: that there came a time like some of the sexual allegations are fuzzy with her but there came a time she said when jeffrey epstein brought her to meet donald trump like during the period when we're told that she was
a sex slave now
Speaker 9: that's not well known among maga right um so there's like if you wanted to there's definitely more than enough material for you to make the most damning possible narrative
that would
Speaker 9: seemingly
Speaker 23: implicate donald trump on some level you know the miss teen usa stuff and how that intersected with epstein's like involvement in victoria's secret model
Speaker 10: we'll procurement them, whatever.
Speaker 10: But in terms of like what MAGA was being told on this podcast circuit with like where Cash Patel would go on Benny Johnson or Bongino would give his spin on it from the Rumble platform, Donald Trump was supposed to be the hero,
Speaker 23: right? Obviously, again, that was just another like layer of myth that got grafted onto it that was conducive to what MAGA wanted to believe and also just as fact avoid as the rest of the mythology. But that's what pretty much happened and then it got framed as like this is more about the Democratic elite.
Speaker 10: So, you know, Bill Gates, Bill Clinton, Reid
Hall,
Speaker 10: Hoffman, X, Y, and Z, right? The W.E.F., you know, who else? I mean, Larry Summers.
Speaker 52: Stephen
Speaker 159: Hawking. Well,
I guess
Speaker 10: Stephen
Speaker 52: Hawking, but like Epstein himself was seen to me maybe more of a Democrat of sorts, even though he wasn't like really overtly political in any way. And
Woman 58: like,
so I think
Woman 58: that, I think that explains it, right? I think it's just how, how easily this thing
Speaker 36: as a mega,
Speaker 23: all encompassing mega narrative with like a choose your own adventure, like little slant,
was
Speaker 23: able to have projected onto it this
Speaker 10: trump exonerating side plot right that uh ended up colliding with that reality once he got back into office in the
Speaker 60: second term and what ended up happening was not this like dramatic avenger style like uh deep stage redemption tale that some of the
Speaker 125 (lower-pitched voice): podcast creatures had ginned up anticipation for
I think
Speaker 62: it was a massive mistake by Trump to campaign on releasing the Epstein files. I think it
was
Speaker 161: a massive mistake to release them. He hardly mentioned it. It was his dopey surrogates. And I think it was a mistake not just for him
Speaker 62: politically, but I think it was a mistake for justice. And I think a lot of people have been caught up in a witch hunt that didn't deserve it. There's been a lot more injustice created. There probably still will be
Speaker 46: more. Trump's consigliere, the guy who was the chief strategist for his 2016 campaign and was his top advisor for the first nine months of the fascination.
Speaker 46: first term and is still like a consultant and like the leader of MAGA you know who I'm talking about Steve Bannon I don't know that anybody had a closer relationship with Jeffrey Epstein and Steve Bannon at least at the period where they were acquainted I mean they were texting each other seemingly
all day
Speaker 46: every day they're like teenage girls or something in terms of how giddy they were to have this like little uh you know friendship bracelet relationship with one another it's amazing so you that's another thing you could tie in with Trump right and people weren't aware of
Speaker 162: that when this mythology was getting sort of like incubated
so it's
Speaker 162: just amazing
Speaker 1: Thank
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): you.
Speaker 162: And the
Speaker 104: worst part about releasing these things is that no one thought
Speaker 21: it through and understood, not just that this was going to dominate the news cycle forever and ever. And it would give the left
Speaker 1: everything they ever dreamed of, even though it's not true, the vast majority of it, but also you're not going to be able to release all
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): the so-called files, which will always leave open the massive door for those who will say, ah, ah,
Speaker 32 (higher-pitched voice): The really good stuff was still being part of the cover up.
I
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): mean, so you're never going to get they get
no credit
Speaker 75 (higher-pitched voice): for the disclosure at all. Zero. I mean, the only reason why we know any of this stuff is because Trump's DOJ released it. And yet somehow there's still going to be people saying they totally don't know the real good stuff because they didn't release the
Speaker 163: files. It was an inherently stupid thing to do.
Speaker 96: And they totally bungled the redaction process, as I sort of tried to
Speaker 86: explain in part. That was inevitable. That was
Speaker 164: inevitable. Well, not necessarily. Not if you passed a bill that said just one line, release the Epstein files. Wasn't that the slogan? Wasn't that what everybody was chanting?
Speaker 165: You can't do that. You could not
Speaker 156 (higher-pitched voice): have done that.
Why
Speaker 166: not?
Speaker 156 (higher-pitched voice): For lots of reasons. First of all, protecting accusers. Number two. But you could have overridden that. It was a standalone statute.
Speaker 167: OK, I'm not I'm saying based upon the law that got passed, it was impossible to redact these things properly. I know I'm saying if
Speaker 96: the law had been passed in a more straightforward, you know, non bloated way with all these ridiculous superfluous exceptions. There's a reason why this
Speaker 50: never becomes public. If the if the Nancy Guthrie file ever comes out, we're going to find out that Trump was implicated. Epstein was implicated. JFK Jr. was implicated. Elvis Presley was implicated. I mean, in the
Speaker 170: disappearance of Nancy Guthrie, Tupac.
Speaker 170: probably so because
Speaker 93: that's my point is if you're going to do it like because it was going to get done it was happening like it was in progress right if
Speaker 9: you're going to do it then just do it do the full disclosure right which of course couldn't be done because there
Speaker 10: has to be this dogmatic deference to anybody and their mother and uncle and like second cousin who can claim that they were some at some point within two football fields of jeffrey epstein and they are therefore a victim
Speaker 151: michael thank you so much for your time i'm just going to make one last plea
Speaker 21: Please take a close – I know you have already taken a good look at it, but take a closer look at the Penn State Sandusky case when you finally get time. The parallels to Andrew are very strong, and the injustice was just as great, if not greater, because
Speaker 71: there were no actual crimes committed in that case. So will you please do that if you can? I
Speaker 95: will. I have. I mean we've been over this, but yes, I take – I accept – I'm taking it under advisement, okay?
All right. Thanks,
Speaker 71: Michael. You take care.